



23, Mettu Street, Velachery, Chennai – 42



+91 8778079644



musanthosh1999@gmail.com

OBJECTIVE

A Seasoned IT Professional with 3 years of experience, seeking a carrier in an esteemed organization that provides challenging environment to utilize my expertise and ensures a continuous learning process and provide exposure to new ideas that stimulate personal and professional growth.



SANTHOSH M

EXPERIENCE

Nextazy Solution Private Limited | DevOps Engineer Nov 2020 – Oct 2023

D4Insight Private Limited | Engineer - IT Oct 2023 - Present

EDUCATION

Bachelor of Engineering – First Class (2016-2020) Government College of Engineering, Thanjavur.

Higher Secondary Certificate (Bio-Maths) (89%) (2014- 2016) Dhanalaksmi Srinivasan Higher secondary school, Perambalur.

TECHNOLOGIES

- Operating Systems: Linux Ubuntu, CentOS, Debian, Amazon Linux 2 and Amazon Linux 3
- Cloud: AWS, GCP, Azure
- Python for Automation
- Docker and Docker Swarm
- Kubernetes
- Bitbucket
- Jenkins
- SonarQube
- Prometheus and Grafana
- Jira
- MongoDB
- MySQL
- Nagios
- Portainer

INTERESTS

- Networking
- Terraform
- CI/CD
- Scripting
- IAC Infrastructure as Code
- Cloud Services
- Migration
- LLM Model Deployment

DEVOPS ENGINEER – NEXTAZY SOLUTIONS PVT LTD

- Responsible for architecting, designing, implementing and supporting cloud-based infrastructure and its solutions.
- Created NAT gateways and instances to allow communication from the private instances to the internet through bastion hosts.
- Created VPC Networks and configured its Subnets, Routes, VPC Peering, Firewall Rules/Security Groups in AWS and GCP
- Used security groups, network ACL's, internet gateways and route tables to ensure a secure zone for organization in AWS public cloud.
- Created and Configured Cloud Identify Organization setup with Organizations projects, Folders with required IAM permissions.
- Repository Creation in Bitbucket.
- Managed Continuous Integration using Jenkins and Bitbucket.
- Created a local image repository to avoid the containers pulling the image every time from Docker Hub.
- Configured Jenkins Master and Build Slaves as Docker Container.
- Installed SonarQube on the environment and integrated with Jenkins, Bitbucket and performed automatic sonar analysis.
- Configured S3 buckets with various life cycle policies to archive the infrequently accessed data to storage classes based on requirement.
- Possess good knowledge in creating and launching EC2 instances using AMI's of Linux, Ubuntu, RHEL and wrote shell scripts to bootstrap instance.
- Created snapshots to take backups of the volumes and images to store launch configurations of the EC2.
- Responsible for Continuous Integration and Continuous Delivery process implementation using Jenkins along with Python and Shell scripts to automate routine jobs.
- Implemented DNS through route 53 to have highly available and scalable applications.
- Automated SonarQube to provide Pull Request approvals on Bitbucket.
- Implemented Branching Strategy on the Bitbucket.
- Implemented CICD pipeline for the Staging.
- Configuration of Nginx Ingress controller in GKE for path-based parameters.
- Installation and Configuration of RabbitMQ message-broker queuing protocol.
- Configuration of Grafana and Prometheus for Microservices monitoring, node exporter and Blackbox exporter for Instance performance monitor.
- Alerts setup in Grafana from CloudWatch metrics and logs. Status OK service integration with Influx DB for API Get Session monitoring and Alerts.
- Co-ordinating with Development leads and provide solutions for the integration & automation.
- Implemented Jenkins application Backup.
- Implemented Release process automation by integrating Jenkins, Bitbucket, SonarQube and ECS.
- Installation and up gradation of OS, Kernel and additional Packages using RPM and YUM
- User administration and password policy management.
- Knowledge in booting and shutdown procedure.
- Monitoring server performance and application process.
- Handling of File System management and ACL and Backup Tools.
- Troubleshooting Linux, User and Group management.
- Configuring crontab and scheduling the jobs.

ENGINEER IT – D4 INSIGHT PRIVATE LIMITED

- Responsible for architecting, designing, implementing and supporting cloud-based infrastructure and its solutions.
- Created NAT gateways and instances to allow communication from the private instances to the internet through bastion hosts.
- Created VPC Networks and configured it's Subnets, Routes, VPC Peering, Firewall Rules/Security Groups in AWS and GCP
- Involved in configuration of Amazon Lambda to manage some of the AWS services.
- Used security groups, network ACL's, internet gateways and route tables to ensure a secure zone for organization in AWS public cloud.
- Created and configured Elastic load balancers and auto scaling groups to distribute the traffic and to have a cost efficient, fault tolerant and highly available environment.
- Created and Configured Cloud Identify Organization setup with Organizations projects, Folders with required IAM permissions.
- Repository migration from GitHub to Bitbucket.
- Managed Continuous Integration using Jenkins and Bitbucket.
- Created a local image repository to avoid the containers pulling the image every time from Docker Hub.
- Responsible for Cloud Armor security policies and Transport Layer Security in GCP
- Migrated Free style projects to Jenkins pipeline jobs
- Configured Jenkins Master and Build Slaves as Docker Container
- Integrated Jenkins running in AWS EC2 to deploy the Code into GCP Artifact Registry authenticated with GCP service account by providing required roles.
- Installed SonarQube on the environment and integrated with Jenkins, Bitbucket and performed automatic sonar analysis.
- Configured S3 buckets with various life cycle policies to archive the infrequently accessed data to storage classes based on requirement.
- Possess good knowledge in creating and launching EC2 instances using AMI's of Linux, Ubuntu, RHEL, and Windows and wrote shell scripts to bootstrap instance.
- Created snapshots to take backups of the volumes and images to store launch configurations of the EC2.
- Responsible for Continuous Integration and Continuous Delivery process implementation using Jenkins along with Python and Shell scripts to automate routine jobs.
- Implemented DNS through route 53 to have highly available and scalable applications.
- Automated SonarQube to provide Pull Request approvals on Bitbucket.
- Automated Unit test cases of Python code by creating a virtual machine.
- Implemented Branching Strategy on the Bitbucket.
- Implemented CICD pipeline for the Staging.
- Worked on the Disaster Recovery implementation for the ECS.
- Building Zookeeper cluster based on the requirement and creating the connectivity between the nodes.
- Installation of 3 Node Solr Cluster and Standalone Solr and maintaining the cluster in AWS and GCP
- Creating Ingress for multiple backend services in Google Kubernetes Engine.
- Configuration of Nginx Ingress controller in GKE for path-based parameters.
- Configuration of OpenSearch for Elasticsearch, Logstash & Kibana.
- Installation and Configuration of RabbitMQ message-broker queuing protocol in GKE.
- Configuration of Grafana and Prometheus for Microservices monitoring, node exporter and Blackbox exporter for Instance performance monitor.
- Configuration of Palo Alto VM Series in Virtual Machines in AWS and GCP
- Alerts setup in Grafana from CloudWatch metrics and logs. Status OK service integration with Influx DB for API GetSession monitoring and Alerts.
- Installation of 3 node Kafka and Zookeeper for continuous event store with high availability
- Troubleshooting the application issues between the ECS services.
- Co-ordinating with Development leads and provide solutions for the integration & automation.
- Implemented Jenkins application Backup.
- Implemented Release process automation by integrating Jenkins, Bitbucket, SonarQube and ECS.

RECENT ACHIEVEMENTS

- Create a sftp server in GCP and configure with cloud storage bucket for storing data to that bucket.
- Create a Jenkins job automation for ECS task steady state check.
- Create a python script for integration with Microsoft teams and AWS ECS service restart.
- Jenkins SAML Authentication for users in Azure App registrations.

PERSONAL PROFILE

Name: Santhosh MDate of Birth: 05.11.1999

Gender: MaleNationality: Indian

• Father Name: Murugan K

• Languages Known: Tamil, English, Telugu

• Permanent Address: 833, Main Road, Udayanatham, Ariyalur – 612 902.

DECLARATION

I hereby declare that the above-mentioned information is correct up to my knowledge and I bear the responsibility for the correctness of the above-mentioned particulars.

Place: Chennai Signature